Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 13; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Repairs not advancing as he could wish. Arrival of Mr. Lee. Franklin's letter of introduction presented to him by Mr. Lockyer. Will do all of his power to make the passage pleasant for Capt. [Thomas] Hutchins and Mr. Brown. Dr. Bancroft not yet arrived. Has given order to Mr. Blodget, the purser, to deliver Capt. Landais's things.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 14; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Estaing, Charles-Henri, comte d'. Paris
    The opportunities of paying his respects to Franklin are too precious to permit of his losing one of them; will dine at Passy with Franklin the next day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    In the name of their charming friend, reminds Franklin of his promises to procure for her children letters of credit on New England, as well as his other promise to dine with her. News received from Brest relative to the additions made to the fleet; report from Cadiz that the Spaniards would not be able to sail for over a week.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Grand, Henry. Paris
    Franklin's accounts and the difficulty of separating them from debts incurred on the public account before his arrival. Eight cases of type arrived for him at Amsterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Enclosing a copy of the only bill of ransom with which he has ever been concerned; had no other motives for ransoming Mr. Dryburugh's vessel but compassion for his helpless family and as a reward for his good services as pilot on the British coast. Concerning Mr. Ross's proposal to take on board the "Alliance" at Noirmoutier, 120 bales of public stores.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 15; L.S. 2p.; Sonnemaens, M.A. de (née Baronne de Wolff). Venlo
    Asking for news of her brother, the Baron de Wülff[en], who went to America as aide-de-camp to General Washington; their last letter from him was dated North Carolina, April 29th, 1778; as they are about to divide the family estate they are anxious to know into whose hands to confide his portion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 15; A.L.S. 1p.; J.F. Frin and Co. Paris
    Concerning bills of Congress; two not accepted owing to certain signatures being wanting; offer to guarantee the payment of these.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Introducing Mr. Appleton, the son of Nathaniel Appleton, director of the Continental Loan Office in Boston, and highly esteemed for his public and private virtues; the son is no dishonor to his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre. Versailles
    Had be been master of his own time, would have paid his respects to Franklin at an earlier date. Encloses a letter from [William] Carmichael.
  - to Concad-Alexander Gerald, 1780 March 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Keith, Robert. St. Pierre, Martinique
    The frigate, "Confederacy," almost ready for sea. Inquiries about a box of furs belonging to him which he fears may have been delivered by mistake to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sending him the beautiful, rare and elegant copy of the Utrecht Union, for the archives of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 18; L.S. (by his wife, Catherine Hocquet). 3p.; Kitchine, Jean. Paimboeuf
    Entreating Franklin's influence to obtain his release from the maritime service of the King of France; his refusal of a perfidious offer made him by the English has exposed him to their vengeance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 19; L.S. 4p.; Haines, R. London
    A long account of his intimacy with the governess in Mr. Izard's family, of that gentleman's finally hounding him out of France, where he had a good business as English map and print seller in Paris; if Franklin will promise him a fair trial, will surrender himself in any port of France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 19; L.S. 4p.; Ross, Samuel et al. L'Orient
    Three American seamen, former members of the crew of the Continental ship "Reprisal," who are in a destitute condition, appeal to Franklin for the prize money due them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1778 March 19; L in 3d P. 1p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Presenting him with the promised walking-stick.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 19; A.L.S. 3p.; Fontallard, —, baronne de. Versailles
    Her unfortunate situation; left a widow with nine children, all of whom are settled except two; her small pension from the Grand Duke of Tuscany insufficient for their support; begs Franklin to second her request to the King for a pension, and also to find out if a letter of hers ever reached the Count d'Estaing, as it contained important papers, which she wishes returned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumenil, Pierre. Havre
    Writes on behalf of an Irish Captain, who is a prisoner of war at Havre, and who desires to go over to the American side, and hoist the American flag, if Franklin will put him in the position to do it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Sorry the clothing has not yet arrived; hopes the whole will soon be sent to America; thinks this intelligence will be very agreeable to the army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Holker, Johns. Rouen
    Enclosing the prices of lead as sold in that market; urges Franklin to visit them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 22; A.D.S. 1p.; Peirce, Jeremiah. Passy
    Receipt for eight louis d'or, lent him by Franklin, to enable him to return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Dieche, Chevalier. Saint-Martory
    Begging for news of the Chevalier de Villefranche, who went to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Hopes, Jno. L'Orient
    Writes on behalf of himself and fifteen other men, exchanged from Plymouth out of Mill Prison; destitute of money and clothes; begs Franklin to advance them a small sum to be deducted out of their wages and prize money in the Continental service; the names of the released prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Besides the copy of the Utrecht Union, sends him some philosophic books, and a packet for Capt. Jones.
    (In English.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Flaghac, Capt. — de. Strasbourg
    Has written to M. le Prince de Montbarrey, asking for a leave of absence of three years, in order to enter the American service; his reasons for wishing to take this step; begs Franklin's assistance to enable him to carry out his plan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Hopes nothing will interfere with the exchange of prisoners. The people of England not averse to a reconciliation with America, only deceived by the acts of their Ministers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Chavannes, -------. Versailles
    Takes the liberty of enclosing a letter sent to him by M. Olry, in order that it may reach its destination in safety.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. Fra[ncis] Lewis. 1p; The Board of Admiralty. Philadelphia
    The detachment of four ships to guard the harbor of Charleston has subjected their coasts to the depredations of the enemy's armed vessels from New York; the Board therefore desire that the "Alliance" may be ordered to Philadelphia with any supplies now in readiness for the army and navy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Gridley, Joseph. Nantes
    Desiring an order to enable him to obtain a passage to America on board the "Alliance"; Mr. Jonathan Williams's change of plans leaves his berth vacant; his health poor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; L.S. 1p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Acknowledging Franklin's orders of the 18th current; has written to Nantes for particular information respecting the anchorage of Noirmoutier; the cannon all on board. Refers to Dr. Bancroft for an account of certain circumstances concerning his conduct in Holland. Afraid Franklin will find "busybody C-----" less worthy than he formerly imagined.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Enclosing a declaration [1 p.] by the States of Friesland in which they agree to the resolution for unlimited convoys, even for building timber. Memoir presented by Mr. [Joseph] Y[orke]. Political situation in Russia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    His letter to Mr. Carmichael has been intercepted and is in the hands of the French Ambassador; its contents reflects on Sir Geo. Grand's good faith towards the Americans; cannot possibly furnish proof of his suspicions; overwhelmed at the result of his own imprudence, complete retraction demanded by the Ambassador, M. de La Vauguyon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Much concerned to find that the cartel vessel has returned from Morlaix without a single prisoner in exchange; the Board of Sick and Hurt disgusted at such an outcome of the business; the French Commissary of Marines at Morlaix gave the master of the vessel a receipt for the hundred American prisoners, but said he had no authority to return any English ones; until this matter is cleared up, all further steps must be at an end.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Servandony, —, de. Paris
    Offering Franklin an invention of his own for erecting a battery of cannon on land or sea to a height of twenty or thirty feet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Collins, Charles. Cherbourg
    Taken prisoner in 1778 on the Continental brig "Resistance," while serving as midshipman; his barbarous treatment by the English; his refusal to enter their service; his subsequent escape from Pembroke Prison and his arrival in France; begs for a little money; is ready to go on board any Continental vessel.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Ritchie, Juliana. Cambray
    Fears that Franklin's continued silence means that something has happened to her husband which he does not choose to tell her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 29; A.L.S. 4p.; Gaisberg, Capt. —, baron de, and Ferdinand de Stahel. Babócsa, Hungary
    Their ardent wish is to enter the American army; only waiting for the promise of Franklin's protection to start at once for Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Blackit, Peter. Dinan prison
    Was lately boatswain on board the "Princess" privateer; accused of conspiring with certain English prisoners on board to take possession of the ship; has been sent from prison to prison, and is now in daily fear of being sent to England; declares the charge against him false, and begs Franklin to let him have a lawful trial; amount of prize money due him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 30; L.S. 2p.; Roussille, Pierre. Paris
    Prevented from going to Bordeaux by severe illness. Applies once more for a small loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 31; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Urgent need of despatching the judgements for certain prizes as quickly as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of October 22d, recommending to his notice the affairs of M. De Lafreté with Mr. Roulbac, of Edenton; promises to do everything in his power.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March; A.L.S. 1p.; Fleury, Lieut.-Col. François Louis Teisseidre
    Obliged to join his regiment at Brest; begs Franklin to send the silver medal which Congress voted for him, to his father, who will receive it in his absence; desires to have a gold one struck off from the same die at his own expense, if Franklin has no objection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 4; A.L. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Going to Versailles for the last time before his departure; desires Franklin's despatches that night.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Dorsett, William. Post-marked Havre
    American sailor, taken prisoner and carried to New York; escaped to France where he is once more a prisoner; begs for assistance to obtain his freedom.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Dowlin, Patrick. Roscow
    Forced through lack of provisions to liberate twenty-one men; two of the enemy's packets taken; on the 19th ult. was joined by his consort, the "Princess." Ill conduct of the French on board his vessel; they acted neither as soldiers nor sailors, and contrary to the contract between the United States and France; hopes to reach Dunkirk shortly, if the number of his crew, weakened as they are by the departure of the French, will permit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Malony, Thomas. Ancenis
    Taken prisoner by Captain Jones; served him as pilot on board the "Surf"; sufferings he endured; begs for his exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridout, Thomas. Bordeaux
    Embarked from Baltimore the 26th of December, 1779; encloses a letter entrusted to him by Mr. Carroll; his vessel detained two months by the frost.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 4; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Steps he has taken to receive certain stores on board the "Alliance." Concerning the conduct of M. C—; fears that Franklin has been deceived in him; a dishonorable proposition made by him; loth to expose his conduct and willing to give him time repent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 5; L.S. 2p.; Puchelberg and Co. L'Orient
    All the English prisoners transferred to Dinan, except one sick boy in the hospital. The repartition of the prizes not yet having been arranged, several officers on the "Alliance" are in want of money; only await orders to furnish them with the necessary funds.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 5 and 13; D.S. Cha[rle] Thomson, Sec[retary]s. 1p., and L. S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Report of Board of Treasury that eight sets of bills of exchange, drawn in favor of Thomas McKean, had been destroyed to prevent falling into the hands of the enemy, and order by Congress for their replacement. Accompanied by a letter from the Treasurer of Loans to the American Commissioners notifying them of the issuance of the bills.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; David, ------, l’aîné. Versailles
    Wrote Franklin nearly a year before, enclosing a letter from his friend, M. Montaudouin, and asking for the position of Consul or Agent at Morlaix; as he knows English, feels sure he could be useful to the American prisoners, now being exchanged from England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 6; A.L.S. 4p.; Van der Perre and Meyners. Middelburg
    Their vessel, the "Berkenbos," most unjustly captured by the "Alliance" and sent to Boston or Philadelphia; claim restitution and damages; the Captain forced by Captain Jones to certify that the ship was English property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Zollickoffer, Jean Conrad. Bordeaux
    During his stay in Philadelphia met Franklin's daughter, and Mr. Hillegas, both of whom confided letters to Franklin to his care which he will forward at once; his time occupied in procuring certain articles for the United States; desires information about the negotiation of bills at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Acknowledging Franklin's favors of the 29th and 31st ult., with the news of the dastardly conduct of Sir Geo. Grand in opening his letter to Mr. Carmichael and then giving it to the French Ambassador; wrote at once to the Ambassador [copy enclosed, 3 p.] regretting only the part which reffered to him personally, and promising to keep the other matter secret, in accordance with Franklin's request. Russia's offer to unite with Holland in protecting the commerce of neutral nations from England's aggression.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Reyhermann, -----. Wersdorf near Apold, Saxe-Weimar
    Concerning pensions for widows and orphans, with mention of an alchemist's discovery of a never-ceasing source of gold.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Reyhermann, -----. Wersdorf near Apold, Saxe-Weimar
    Thinks his ms. and printed dedications, sent one and one half years ago, must either have been received or purloined by his enemies. Alchemistic discovery. Asks for 6 or 10 louis d'ors.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 7; A.L.S. 3P.; Reyhermann, -----. Wersdorf near Apold
    Concerning the publication of his alchemistic work. Asks that 6 or 10 louis d'ors be sent him to continue printing his work.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 8; A.L.S. 2p.; MacCreery, William. Bordeaux
    Sends the newspapers and journals of Congress, received from Mr. Lovell, by Captain De Freÿ; warns Franklin against the Baron Roustellen who may present himself at Passy and who is known to be an inveterate enemy of the United States, said to be summoned to England for the sake of the information he can supply them with.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Invites Franklin and his grandson to dine with him. Hopes they will not refuse, as he has seen Franklin so seldom during the winter. M. de Malesherbes may be able to come also.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Is deputed to convey the veneration and gratitude of "Messieurs de Deux-Ponts," who are ordered to set sail on the 8th. Report from London announces an explosion of the largest magazine at Port Royal, Jamaica, damaging the fort as well as the vessels in the harbor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 9; A.L.S. 1p.; de Wulffen, Baron. Rotterdam
    Complains of being badly treated in Holland, though under Dr. Franklin's protection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Delleville, Phillippe de
    Writes on behalf of seven Americans who having escaped by bribing the jailor, embarked in a frail boat without sails or rudder and who, with the help of some rags and an old plank, managed to land near Bayeux; their desire to return to America as soon as possible; has written to M. de Sartine but thinks it best to inform Dr. Franklin of the affair; has assisted them in all possible ways.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 10; L.S. 1p.; von Steuben, W. A. Cüstrin
    Rejoices that his son, the General, has written to him and requests the forwarding of the enclosed letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Theobald Jennings and others. Bayeux
    Asking for assistance to enable them to embark for America; their escape from Portsmouth and perilous trip in a small boat, which landed them near Bayeux; kindly treated by the inhabitants; destitute of clothes and the necessaries of life.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    Concerning two bills sent him by Edward Burd, Esq., of Philadelphia, which he encloses for acceptance; hopes that Mr. Burd's having unfortunately neglected to endorse them, will not prevent their being duly honored.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Explanation of the affair between Capt. Jones and the English pilot; encloses certificates [2 p.] signed by Jones [duplicates of those in XXXIX, 138]. Promise of M. Van Berkel to arrange a reconciliation with the Grand Facteur. The Holland Assembly deliberating on Russia's proposal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 11; A.L.S. 1p.; Ricot, Philippe?. St. Valery
    The "Black Prince" forced to land at Berck, on account of being chased by an English frigate; sent an officer there at once to know if he could be of any service; his zeal for the American cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, Jonathan. Lebanon, Conn
    Introducing his son, Col. John Trumbull to Franklin's notice and protection; refers Franklin to him for the political and military news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 13; Dumas, C.G.F.
    The Russsian proposals bid fair to be accepted; attitude of the English party. Holland's unanimous decision for unlimited convoys; aid demanded by the English refused. M. Van Berkel's promise to bring about a reconciliation between the French Ambassador and himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Eckhard, Anthony George. Utrecht
    Wishes to establish factories in other countries; if not feasible at Paris then perhaps in England, in which case he begs for a letter of introduction.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 14; A.L.S. 3p.; Duhil, Even. Nantes
    Holds the commission of Captain in the First South Carolina regiment, Col. Cha[rles] Cotesworth Pinckeny; was forced to return to France on account of his father's death: anxious to procure an immediate passage to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbier, B. Nantes
    Dishonorable conduct of M. Gruel who abused the confidence placed in him by an American, John Green, who obtained the command of Gruel's vessel "Le Patriote" on the condition that he should share the expense of fitting her out; begs Franklin to obtain justice for his friend, Green.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Chantereyne, ----- de. Cherbourg
    Intrusted with the fitting out of the "Black Princess"; desires a letter of recommendation to the Commissaries of Marine at Havre and Cherbourg, in order to obtain sailors now in various prisons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Logan ,George. London
    Announcing his safe arrival; Mr. Barclay, who has charge of his affairs, thinks they can be settled in a month; expects to sail for America on a Dutch vessel. Refers Franklin to Mr. Digg[e]s for an account of public affairs; many not yet convinced of the necessity of acknowledging the independence of the United States. Interview he had with Mr. Hartley, who expected to make a motion in regard to America the next day, in order to force the Ministry into some explanation of their future course of action.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Giving an account of the loss of the "Black Prince"; all due to the stupid and villainous chase, made by the "Calonne," commanded by the ignorant Capt. Guilman; hopes Franklin will report his conduct to the Minister of Navy; would sooner sell his last shirt than not procure a large cutter for the intrepid and clever Capt. Dowlin.
    Printed in part in Hale's "Franklin in france," I, 312.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Roused that morning at four o'clock by the arrival of Mr. Montplaisir and Capt. Jones from L'Orient; the latter has lain down for a little needed sleep; supposes he will call on Franklin as soon as he is called and dressed. The enclosed letter from Mr. Wharton tells everything except that the King's officers at L'Orient have begun to cut up and pull down part of the internal partition of the "Serapis"; this has greatly increased the discontent of the "Alliance's" crew.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 April 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Result of the attempted reconciliation between the Ambassador and himself; unable to accede to the former's demand that he should apologize to Sir G[eo. Grand]. Russia's proposals accepted by the Holland Assembly.